<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;शिक्षा on संस्कृते विश्वासटिप्पणयः</title>
    <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/sanskrit/shixaa/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;शिक्षा on संस्कृते विश्वासटिप्पणयः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vvasuki.github.io/sanskrit/shixaa/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Labial oṣṭhya</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/sanskrit/shixaa/labial/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/sanskrit/shixaa/labial/</guid>
      <description>v: labial or dento-labial Phonetic drift  It could have been a bi-labial ; but we have no positive proof to that effect. &amp;hellip;. Siddheshwar Varma ( 1929), p. 129, says: &amp;quot; For at least a thousand years before Brugmann, Indian grammarians had observed, and correctly, that the Sanskrit v in the medial and final positions was not a labio-dental.&amp;quot; The Dantyoṣṭhyavidhi , p. 4, provides lists of variation between pure labial and labio-dental varieties of v and b in the Atharvaveda .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>उच्चारण-परिवर्तनम्</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/sanskrit/shixaa/uchchAraNa-parivartanam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/sanskrit/shixaa/uchchAraNa-parivartanam/</guid>
      <description>परिवर्तनक्रमः    phonetic transformation     phonetic transformation text    &amp;ldquo;The orthodox Indian tradition has greatly respected the relationship of a teacher and his disciple and has continued to believe that nothing ever changed in this oral transmission. It is believed that the oral text has been handed down from one generation to the next without any changes. However, we must view a preliterate oral tradition with a fresh linguistic and analytical approach.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ऐ औ</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/sanskrit/shixaa/ai-au/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/sanskrit/shixaa/ai-au/</guid>
      <description>सन्ध्यक्षर+उच्चारणम् (&amp;ldquo;एओ=अइ/ अउ, ऐऔ=आइ/ आउ&amp;rdquo;) इति विषये अत्र TW, MB। &amp;ldquo;By the time of patanjali (classical saMskRta) the ए ओ were monophthongs, but ऐ औ were diphthongs. We know this because patanjali describes this. I don&amp;rsquo;t know about the RgvedaprAtishAkhya or the Rktantra - they would be prior to patanjali, but also when classical sanskrit had come to be spoken&amp;hellip; patanjali (already classical) mentions that people from the राणायणीय stream pronounced a short version of ए.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>छन्दः</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/sanskrit/shixaa/chandas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/sanskrit/shixaa/chandas/</guid>
      <description>चर्चास्पदानि  यतौ च पादान्ते विसन्धि-दोषे अत्र। &amp;ldquo;प्रह्रे वा&amp;rdquo; इति लघुत्व-विकल्पे च विषमपादान्ते लघोः गुर्वीकरणे अत्र, अत्र च। वैदिक-प्रयोगेषु च्छन्दसाम् अक्षराधिक्यं न्यूनता वा, तत्संज्ञाश्च - चर्चा, छन्दःशास्त्रे ऽत्र। अन्याश् चर्चास्पद-विषया व्याकरण-आर्षप्रयोगादि-विषयका अत्र।  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>तालु</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/sanskrit/shixaa/tAluH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/sanskrit/shixaa/tAluH/</guid>
      <description> तालु-मूर्धयोस् स्थाने विवादः - दन्तमूर्धयोर् मध्ये ताल्व् इति केचित्, दन्त-ताल्वोर् मध्ये मूर्धेत्य् अपरे (श्रीरमणशर्मणः शिक्षाप्रथमक्लृप्तौ)। परपक्ष उत्तरो भाति। सम्पदानन्दमिश्रो ऽत्र।     kaNTha-tAlu-mUrdhA-1     kaNTha-tAlu-mUrdhA-2   </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>मूर्धा</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/sanskrit/shixaa/mUrdhA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/sanskrit/shixaa/mUrdhA/</guid>
      <description>Retroflex-पक्षः  जिह्वाया अधोभागसंस्पर्शेन मूर्धन्यवर्णा जन्यन्त, ऊर्ध्वभागसंस्पर्शेन तालव्यादिवर्णा इति निश्चयेनालम् मन्ये। णकारस् तु मूर्धां विना दुष्कर उच्चरितुम्। &amp;ldquo;the dental, palatal, and retroflex sounds show a clear hierarchy. dental &amp;lt; palatal &amp;lt; retroflex&amp;rdquo;  &amp;ldquo;Panini’s rule 8.4.40 ( स्तोः श्चुनाश्चुः) says that a dental stop or sibilant is replaced by the corresponding palatal stop or sibilant if followed or preceded by a palatal stop or sibilant, e.g., तच्च .&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;A palatal never becomes a dental.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>विसर्गः</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/sanskrit/shixaa/visargaH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/sanskrit/shixaa/visargaH/</guid>
      <description>प्रातिशाख्येषु संज्ञा  (स्रोतांसि - राकेशवचनानि) तैत्तिरीयप्रातिशाख्यस्य वैदिकाभरणभाष्ये उच्यते यत् &amp;ldquo;वायोर्विसर्जनेन जन्यत्वाद् अयं विसर्जनीयो भवति&amp;rdquo;। (तै०प्रा०वै०भा० १। १८) ऋक्प्रातिशाख्ये तथा तैत्तिरीयप्रातिशाख्ये यद्यपि विसर्जनीयसंज्ञा न विहिता किन्तु विसर्जनीयशब्दस्य बहुधा प्रयोग उपलभ्यते। वाजसनेयिप्रातिशाख्ये तथा ऋक्तन्त्रे विसर्जनीयसंज्ञा विहिता। (अः इति विसर्जनीयः। वा०प्रा० ८। २२, ऋ०तं० १। २) अथर्वप्रातिशाख्ये विसर्जनीयसंज्ञा न विधीयते। किन्तु विसर्जनीयशब्दस्य प्रयोगः बहुधा समुपलभ्यते। किन्तु, विसर्जनीयस्य कृते अभिनिष्ठानशब्दस्य प्रयोगोऽपि अत्र विहितः। तथाहि– विसर्जनीयोऽभिनिष्ठानः। (च०अ० १। ४२)  स्थानम्  (स्रोतांसि - राकेशवचनानि) ऋक्प्रातिशाख्ये तैत्तिरीयप्रातिशाख्ये (कण्ठस्थानौ हकारविसर्जनीयौ॥२.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ह्रस्व-ऎ-ऒ-कारौ</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/sanskrit/shixaa/hrasva-e-o/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/sanskrit/shixaa/hrasva-e-o/</guid>
      <description>देवनागर्यां चिह्नानि ऎ ऒ ए᳘ ओ᳘
संस्कृते प्रयोगः सूचनास्रोतांसि -
 श्रीरमणशर्मलेखात् -  लोके ऽभावः Patañjali goes on to note that such pronunciation is not found anywhere else either in common (i.e. non-Vedic) Sanskrit or Vedic Sanskrit: नैव हि लोके नाप्यन्यस्मिन् वेदे अर्ध एकारः अर्ध ओकारो वा अस्ति
सामवेदे &amp;ldquo;Patañjali, the traditional authority on Paninian grammar, says in his Mahābhāṣya while commenting on the 3rd Śiva Sūtra ē ōṅ (and once more later while commenting on ēca igghrasvādēśē, Pāṇini 1/1/48): ननु च भोश् छन्दोगानां सात्यमुग्रि-राणायनीयाः अर्धम् एकारम् अर्धम् ओकारṃ च अधीयतॆ – सुजाते ĕश्वसून्ड़्ते, अध्वर्यो ऒद्रिभिः सुतम्, शुक्रṃ ते ऎन्यद् यजतं ते ऎन्यत् – इति</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
