<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Articles on संस्कृते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/articles/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Articles on संस्कृते विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/articles/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>21st century learning - shashi</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/articles/shashikiraNa_21stce-approach/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/articles/shashikiraNa_21stce-approach/</guid>
      <description>This paper by Shashi Kiran B N and Hari Ravikumar was presented at the international conference New Frontiers in Sanskrit and Indic Knowledge in June 2017 organized by the Chinmaya International Foundation.
Abstract Sanskrit, one of the greatest gifts of India to the world, is unique in many ways. The Pāṇinian system of grammar, logical in its structure and exhaustive in its delineation, gave the language great strength in terms of word-generation ability, brevity, and freedom from ambiguity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Munshi 1951 speech</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/articles/munshi_1951_speech/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/articles/munshi_1951_speech/</guid>
      <description>Intro  I -  Of all the forces which bind the man and make him a social and cultural being, the most powerful is the ‘Word,’ In that sense, the worship of the Word, Sabda-Brahma, is one of the most all-pervading forces of life. For instance, geographically India owes everything to the Himalayas; in the sphere of social relationships, the mind and the spirit, India owes everything to Sanskrit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RS - Lanka sanskrit</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/articles/seneviratne_lanka-sanskrit/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/articles/seneviratne_lanka-sanskrit/</guid>
      <description>Source - Colombo Telegraph .
What makes one a Sanskrit scholar today?
What areas of the Sanskrit language does one need to be good with to declare “I know Sanskrit”?
Can one become knowledgeable about Sanskrit scholarship without mastering the language?
What could Sanskrit tell us and could not?
Do we really need Sanskrit?
The questions of this sort demand clarification of a few points before being answered. First, Sanskrit scholarship has been a misnomer mainly because one cannot, justifiably, know a certain language without knowing the wealth of knowledge in it, simply because knowledge comes to us getting on a certain language, either oral, written or both, as the vehicle.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>लङ्कायां संस्कृतम्</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/articles/lanka_education/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/sanskrit/meta/articles/lanka_education/</guid>
      <description>Below are excerpts from Rohana Seneviratne&amp;rsquo;s article.
 &amp;ldquo;Buddhist monks from their early Samanera age, are “required” to learn Sanskrit alongside Pali &amp;hellip; it is Pali – not Sanskrit – that is expected to sustain the local version of Theravada Buddhism on this land.&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;The academic contexts where Sanskrit is taught in support of the study of disciplines such as the Sinhala and Tamil languages and literature, History, Religious Studies, Archaeology, and Philosophy often confine Sanskrit scholarship to the basics.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
